In this video, we'll talk about
在这段视频中 我们要讲
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
the normal equation, which for
标准方程法 (Normal Equation)
some linear regression problems, will
对于某些线性回归问题
give us a much better way
用标准方程法求解参数θ的最优值更好
to solve for the optimal value
of the parameters theta.
用标准方程法求解参数θ的最优值更好
Concretely, so far the
具体而言 到目前为止
algorithm that we've been using
我们一直在使用的线性回归的算法
for linear regression is gradient
是梯度下降法
descent where in order
就是说 为了最小化代价函数 J (θ)
to minimize the cost function
J of Theta, we would take
我们使用的迭代算法
this iterative algorithm that takes
需要经过很多步
many steps, multiple iterations of
也就是说通过多次迭代来计算梯度下降
gradient descent to converge
to the global minimum.
来收敛到全局最小值
In contrast, the normal equation
相反地
would give us a method to
标准方程法提供了一种求θ的解析解法
solve for theta analytically, so
that rather than needing to run
所以与其使用迭代算法
this iterative algorithm, we can
我们可以直接一次性求解θ的最优值
instead just solve for the
optimal value for theta
我们可以直接一次性求解θ的最优值
all at one go, so that in
所以说基本上
basically one step you get
一步就可以得到优化值
to the optimal value right there.
It turns out the normal equation
标准方程法有一些优点 也有一些缺点
that has some advantages and
some disadvantages, but before
但是在我们讲解这个
we get to that and talk about
和何时使用标准方程之前
when you should use it, let's
让我们先对这个算法有一个直观的理解
get some intuition about what this method does.
For this week's planetary example, let's
我们举一个例子来解释这个问题
imagine, let's take a
我们假设 有一个非常简单的代价函数J(θ)
very simplified cost function
J of Theta, that's just the
它就是一个实数θ的函数
function of a real number Theta.
So, for now, imagine that Theta
所以现在 假设θ只是一个标量
is just a scalar value or that Theta is just a row value.
或者说θ只有一行
It's just a number, rather than a vector.
它是一个数字 不是向量
Imagine that we have a cost function J that's a quadratic function of this real value
假设我们的代价函数J 是这个实参数θ的二次函数
parameter Theta, so J of Theta looks like that.
所以J (θ) 看起来是这样的
Well, how do you minimize a quadratic function?
那么如何最小化一个二次函数呢?
For those of you that know a little bit of calculus,
对于那些了解一点微积分的同学来说
you may know that the way to
你可能知道
minimize a function is to
最小化的一个函数的方法是
take derivatives and to
对它求导 并且将导数置零
set derivatives equal to zero.
So, you take the derivative of J with respect to the parameter of Theta.
所以对J求关于θ的导数
You get some formula which I am not going to derive,
我不打算推导那些公式
you set that derivative
你把那个导数置零
equal to zero, and this
这样你就可以求得
allows you to solve for
使得J(θ)最小的θ值
the value of Theda that minimizes J of Theta.
That was a simpler case
这是数据为实数的
of when data was just real number.
一个比较简单的例子
In the problem that we are interested in, Theta is
在这个问题中 我们感兴趣的是
no longer just a real number,
θ不是一个实数的情况
but, instead, is this
它是一个n+1维的参数向量
n+1-dimensional parameter vector, and,
a cost function J is
并且 代价函数J是这个向量的函数
a function of this vector
value or Theta 0 through
也就是θ0到θm的函数
Theta m. And, a cost
一个代价函数看起来是这样
function looks like this, some square cost function on the right.
像右边的这个平方代价函数
How do we minimize this cost function J?
我们如何最小化这个代价函数J?
Calculus actually tells us
实际上 微积分告诉我们一种方法
that, if you, that
one way to do so, is
对每个参数θ求J的偏导数
to take the partial derivative of J, with respect to every parameter of Theta J in turn, and then, to set
all of these to 0.
然后把它们全部置零
If you do that, and you
如果你这样做
solve for the values of
并且求出θ0 θ1 一直到θn的值
Theta 0, Theta 1,
up to Theta N, then,
并且求出θ0 θ1 一直到θn的值
this would give you that values
这样就能得到能够最小化代价函数J的θ值
of Theta to minimize the cost
function J.  Where, if
这样就能得到能够最小化代价函数J的θ值
you actually work through the
如果你真的做完微积分和求解参数θ0到θn
calculus and work through
the solution to the parameters
如果你真的做完微积分和求解参数θ0到θn
Theta 0 through Theta N, the
derivation ends up being somewhat involved.
这个偏微分最终可能很复杂
And, what I am going
接下来我在视频中要做的
to do in this video,
is actually to not go
实际上不是遍历所有的偏微分
through the derivation, which is kind
of long and kind of involved, but
因为这样太久太费事
what I want to do is just
我只是想告诉你们
tell you what you need to know
你们想要实现这个过程所需要知道内容
in order to implement this process
so you can solve for the
这样你就可以解出
values of the thetas that
偏导数为0时θ的值
corresponds to where the
partial derivatives is equal to zero.
偏导数为0时θ的值
Or alternatively, or equivalently,
换个方式说 或者等价地
the values of Theta is that
这个θ能够使得代价函数J(θ)最小化
minimize the cost function J of Theta.
I realize that some of
我发现可能只有熟悉微积分的同学
the comments I made that made
more sense only to those
比较容易理解我的话
of you that are normally familiar with calculus.
So, but if you don't
所以 如果你不了解
know, if you're less familiar
或者不那么了解微积分
with calculus, don't worry about it.
也不必担心
I'm just going to tell you what
我会告诉你
you need to know in order to
要实现这个算法并且使其正常运行
implement this algorithm and get it to work.
你所需的必要知识
For the example that I
举个例子
want to use as a running
我想运行这样一个例子
example let's say that
假如说我有m=4个训练样本
I have m = 4 training examples.
In order to implement this normal
为了实现标准方程法
equation at big, what I'm going to do is the following.
我要这样做
I'm going to take my
看我的训练集
data set, so here are my four training examples.
在这里就是这四个训练样本
In this case let's assume that,
在这种情况下 我们假设
you know, these four examples is all the data I have.
这四个训练样本就是我的所有数据
What I am going to do is take
我所要做的是
my data set and add
在我的训练集中加上一列对应额外特征变量的x0
an extra column that corresponds
to my extra feature, x0,
在我的训练集中加上一列对应额外特征变量的x0
that is always takes
就是那个取值永远是1的
on this value of 1.
What I'm going to do is
接下来我要做的是
I'm then going to construct
构建一个矩阵X
a matrix called X that's
这个矩阵基本包含了训练样本的所有特征变量
a matrix are basically contains all
of the features from my
这个矩阵基本包含了训练样本的所有特征变量
training data, so completely
所以具体地说
here is my here are
这里有我所有的特征变量
all my features and we're
going to take all those numbers and
我们要把这些数字
put them into this matrix "X", okay?
全部放到矩阵中X中 好吧？
So just, you know, copy
所以只是
the data over one column
每次复制一列的数据
at a time and then I am going to do something similar for y's.
我要对y做类似的事情
I am going to take the
我要对我们将要预测的值
values that I'm trying to
predict and construct now
构建一个向量
a vector, like so
像这样的
and call that a vector y.
并且称之为向量y
So X is going to be a
所以X会是一个M*(n+1)维矩阵
m by (n+1) - dimensional matrix, and
Y is going to be
y会是一个m维向量
a m-dimensional vector
where m is the number of training examples
其中m是训练样本数量
and n is, n is
n是特征变量数
a number of features, n+1, because of
n+1是因为我加的这个额外的特征变量x0
this extra feature X0 that I had.
Finally if you take
最后 如??果你用矩阵X和向量y来计算这个
your matrix X and you take
your vector Y, and if you
最后 如??果你用矩阵X和向量y来计算这个
just compute this, and set
θ等于 X转置乘以X的逆 乘以X转置 乘以y
theta to be equal to
X transpose X inverse times
θ等于 X转置乘以X的逆 乘以X转置 乘以y
X transpose Y, this would
give you the value of theta
这样就得到能够使得代价函数最小化的θ
that minimizes your cost function.
There was a lot
幻灯片上的内容比较多
that happened on the slides and
I work through it using one specific example of one dataset.
我讲解了这样一个数据组的一个例子
Let me just write this
让我把这个写成更加通用的形式
out in a slightly more general form
and then let me just, and later on in
在之后的视频中
this video let me explain this equation a little bit more.
我会仔细介绍这个方程
It is not yet entirely clear how to do this.
以防你不完全清楚要如何做
In a general case, let us
在一般情况下
say we have M training examples
假如我们有m个训练样本
so X1, Y1 up to
x1 y1 直到 xn yn
Xn, Yn and n features.
n个特征变量
So, each of the training example
所以每一个训练样本
x(i) may looks like a vector
xi 可能看起来像一个向量
like this, that is a n+1 dimensional feature vector.
像这样一个n+1维特征向量
The way I'm going to construct the
我要构建矩阵X的方法
matrix "X", this is
also called the design matrix
也被称为设计矩阵
is as follows.
如下所示
Each training example gives
每个训练样本给出一个这样的特征向量
me a feature vector like this.
say, sort of n+1 dimensional vector.
也就是说 这样的n+1维向量
The way I am going to construct my
我构建我的设计矩阵X的方法
design matrix x is only construct the matrix like this.
就是构建这样的矩阵
and what I'm going to
那么 我要做的就是
do is take the first
取第一个训练样本
training example, so that's
a vector, take its transpose
也就是一个向量 取它的转置
so it ends up being this,
它最后是这样
you know, long flat thing and
扁长的样子
make x1 transpose the first row of my design matrix.
让x1转置作为我设计矩阵的第一行
Then I am going to take my
然后我要把我的
second training example, x2, take
第二个训练样本x2
the transpose of that and
进行转置 让它作为X的第二行
put that as the second row
of x and so on,
以此类推
down until my last training example.
直到最后一个训练样本
Take the transpose of that,
取它的转置作为矩阵X的最后一行
and that's my last row of
my matrix X. And, so,
取它的转置作为矩阵X的最后一行
that makes my matrix X, an
这样矩阵X就是一个m*(n+1)维矩阵
M by N +1
dimensional matrix.
这样矩阵X就是一个m*(n+1)维矩阵
As a concrete example, let's
举个具体的例子
say I have only one
假如我只有一个特征变量
feature, really, only one
就是说除了x0之外只有一个特征变量
feature other than X zero,
which is always equal to 1.
而x0始终为1
So if my feature vectors
所以如果我的特征向量
X-i are equal to this
xi等于1 也就是x0 和某个实际的特征变量
1, which is X-0, then
some real feature, like maybe the
xi等于1 也就是x0 和某个实际的特征变量
size of the house, then my
比如说房屋大小
design matrix, X, would be equal to this.
那么我的设计矩阵X会是这样
For the first row, I'm going
第一行 就是这个的转置
to basically take this and take its transpose.
So, I'm going to end up with 1, and then X-1-1.
所以最后得到1 然后x(1)1
For the second row, we're going to end
对于第二行 我们得到1 然后x(1)2
up with 1 and then
X-1-2 and so
对于第二行 我们得到1 然后x(1)2
on down to 1, and
这样直到1 然后x(1)m
then X-1-M.
And thus, this will be
这样 这就会是一个m*2维矩阵
a m by 2-dimensional matrix.
So, that's how to construct
所以 这就是如何构建矩阵X 和向量y
the matrix X. And, the
vector Y--sometimes I might
有时我可能会在上面画一个箭头
write an arrow on top to
denote that it is a vector,
来表示这是一个向量
but very often I'll just write this as Y, either way.
但很多时候 我就只写y 是一样的
The vector Y is obtained by
向量y这样求得的
taking all all the labels,
把所有标签
all the correct prices of
所有训练集中正确的房子价格
houses in my training set, and
just stacking them up into
放在一起 得到一个m维向量y
an M-dimensional vector, and
that's Y.  Finally, having
最后 构建完矩阵X和向量y
constructed the matrix X
and the vector Y, we then
我们就可以通过计算X转置乘以X的逆乘以X转置乘以y来得到θ
just compute theta as X'(1/X)
x X'Y. I just
我们就可以通过计算X转置乘以X的逆乘以X转置乘以y来得到θ
want to make
我现在就想确保你明白这个等式
I just want to make sure that this equation makes sense to you
and that you know how to implement it.
并且知道如何实现它
So, you know, concretely, what is this X'(1/X)?
所以具体来说 什么是X的转置乘以X的逆？
Well, X'(1/X) is the
X的转置乘以X的逆是X转置乘以X的逆矩阵
inverse of the matrix X'X.
Concretely, if you were
具体来说
to say set A to
如果你令A等于X转置乘以X
be equal to X' x
X, so X' is a
X的转置是一个矩阵
matrix, X' x X
X的转置乘以X是另一个矩阵
gives you another matrix, and we
call that matrix A. Then, you
我们把这个矩阵称为A
know, X'(1/X) is just
那么 X转置乘以X的逆就是矩阵A的逆
you take this matrix A and you invert it, right!
This gives, let's say 1/A.
也就是1/A
And so that's how you compute this thing.
这就是计算过程
You compute X'X and then you compute its inverse.
先计算X转置乘以X 然后计算它的逆
We haven't yet talked about Octave.
我们还没有谈到Octave
We'll do so in the later
我们将在之后的视频中谈到这个
set of videos, but in the
但是在Octave编程语言
Octave programming language or a
similar view, and also the
或者类似的MATLAB编程语言里是类似的
matlab programming language is very similar.
The command to compute this quantity,
计算这个量的命令
X transpose X inverse times
X转置乘以X的逆乘以X转置乘以y
X transpose Y, is as follows.
的代码命令如下所示
In Octave X prime is
在Octave中 X’表示X转置
the notation that you use to denote X transpose.
And so, this expression that's
这个用红色框起来的表达式
boxed in red, that's computing
计算的是X转置乘以X
X transpose times X.
pinv is a function for
pinv是用来计算逆矩阵的函数
computing the inverse of
a matrix, so this computes
所以这个计算X转置乘以X的逆
X transpose X inverse,
and then you multiply that by
然后乘以X转置 再乘以y
X transpose, and you multiply
that by Y. So you
然后乘以X转置 再乘以y
end computing that formula
这样就算完了这个式子
which I didn't prove,
我没有证明这个式子
but it is possible to
尽管我并不打算这么做
show mathematically even though I'm
但是数学上是可以证明的
not going to do so
这个式子会给出最优的θ值
here, that this formula gives you
the optimal value of theta
这个式子会给出最优的θ值
in the sense that if you set theta equal
就是说如果你令θ等于这个
to this, that's the value
of theta that minimizes the
这个θ值会最小化这个线性回归的代价函数J(θ)
cost function J of theta
for the new regression.
这个θ值会最小化这个线性回归的代价函数J(θ)
One last detail in the earlier video.
最后一点
I talked about the feature
在之前视频中我提到特征变量归一化
skill and the idea of
getting features to be
和让特征变量在相似的范围内的想法
on similar ranges of
Scales of similar ranges of values of each other.
将所有的值归一化在类似范围内
If you are using this normal
如果你使用标准方程发
equation method then feature
那么就不需要归一化特征变量
scaling isn't actually necessary
and is actually okay if,
实际上这是没问题的
say, some feature X one
如果某个特征变量x1在0到1的区间
is between zero and one,
and some feature X two is
某个特征变量x2在0到1000的区间
between ranges from zero to
one thousand and some feature
某个特征变量x2在0到1000的区间
x three ranges from zero
某个特征变量x3在0到10^-5的区间
to ten to the
minus five and if
某个特征变量x3在0到10^-5的区间
you are using the normal equation method
然后如果使用标准方程法
this is okay and there is
这样就没有问题
no need to do features
不需要做特征变量归一化
scaling, although of course
尽管如果你使用梯度下降法
if you are using gradient descent,
then, features scaling is still important.
特征变量归一化仍然很重要
Finally, where should you use the gradient descent
最后 你何时应该使用梯度下降法
and when should you use the normal equation method.
而何时应该使用标准方程法
Here are some of the their advantages and disadvantages.
这里列举了一些它们的优点和缺点
Let's say you have m training
假如你有m个训练样本和n个特征变量
examples and n features.
One disadvantage of gradient descent
梯度下降法的缺点之一就是
is that, you need to choose the learning rate Alpha.
你需要选择学习速率α
And, often, this means running
这通常表示需要运行多次 尝试不同的学习速率α
it few times with different learning
rate alphas and then seeing what works best.
然后找到运行效果最好的那个
And so that is sort of extra work and extra hassle.
所以这是一种额外的工作和麻烦
Another disadvantage with gradient descent
梯度下降法的另一个缺点是
is it needs many more iterations.
它需要更多次的迭代
So, depending on the details,
因为一些细节 计算可能会更慢
that could make it slower, although
there's more to the story as we'll see in a second.
我们一会儿会看到更多的东西
As for the normal equation, you don't need to choose any learning rate alpha.
至于标准方程 你不需要选择学习速率α
So that, you know, makes it really convenient, makes it simple to implement.
所以就非常方便 也容易实现
You just run it and it usually just works.
你只要运行一下 通常这就够了
And you don't need to
并且你也不需要迭代
iterate, so, you don't need
所以不需要画出J(θ)的曲线
to plot J of Theta or
check the convergence or take all those extra steps.
来检查收敛性或者采取所有的额外步骤
So far, the balance seems to
到目前为止
favor normal the normal equation.
天平似乎倾向于标准方程法
Here are some disadvantages of
这里列举一些标准方程法的缺点
the normal equation, and some advantages of gradient descent.
和梯度下降法的优点
Gradient descent works pretty well,
梯度下降法在有很多特征变量的情况下也能运行地相当好
even when you have a very large number of features.
So, even if you
所以即使你有上百万的特征变量
have millions of features you
can run gradient descent and it will be reasonably efficient.
你可以运行梯度下降法 并且通常很有效
It will do something reasonable.
它会正常的运行
In contrast to normal equation, In, in
相对地 标准方程法
order to solve for the parameters
为了求解参数θ 需要求解这一项
data, we need to solve for this term.
We need to compute this term, X transpose, X inverse.
我们需要计算这项X转置乘以X的逆
This matrix X transpose X.
这个X转置乘以X矩阵是一个n*n的矩阵
That's an n by n matrix, if you have n features.
如果你有n个特征变量的话
Because, if you look
因为如果你看一下X转置乘以X的维度
at the dimensions of
X transpose the dimension of
因为如果你看一下X转置乘以X的维度
X, you multiply, figure out what
你可以发现他们的积的维度
the dimension of the product
is, the matrix X transpose
X转置乘以X是一个n*n的矩阵
X is an n by n matrix where
n is the number of features, and
其中 n是特征变量的数量
for almost computed implementations
实现逆矩阵计算所需要的计算量
the cost of inverting
the matrix, rose roughly as
大致是矩阵维度的三次方
the cube of the dimension of the matrix.
So, computing this inverse costs,
因此计算这个逆矩阵需要计算大致n的三次方
roughly order, and cube time.
Sometimes, it's slightly faster than
有时稍微比计算n的三次方快一些
N cube but, it's, you know, close enough for our purposes.
但是对我们来说很接近
So if n the number of features is very large,
所以如果特征变量的数量n很大的话
then computing this
那么计算这个量会很慢
quantity can be slow and
the normal equation method can actually be much slower.
实际上标准方程法会慢很多
So if n is
因此如果n很大
large then I might
usually use gradient descent because
我可能还是会使用梯度下降法
we don't want to pay this all in q time.
因为我们不想花费n的三次方的时间
But, if n is relatively small,
但如果n比较小
then the normal equation might give you a better way to solve the parameters.
那么标准方程法可能更好地求解参数θ
What does small and large mean?
那么怎么叫大或者小呢？
Well, if n is on
那么 如果n是上百的
the order of a hundred, then
inverting a hundred-by-hundred matrix is
计算百位数乘百位数的矩阵
no problem by modern computing standards.
对于现代计算机来说没有问题
If n is a thousand, I would still use the normal equation method.
如果n是上千的 我还会使用标准方程法
Inverting a thousand-by-thousand matrix is
千位数乘千位数的矩阵做逆变换
actually really fast on a modern computer.
对于现代计算机来说实际上是非常快的
If n is ten thousand, then I might start to wonder.
但如果n上万 那么我可能会开始犹豫
Inverting a ten-thousand-  by-ten-thousand matrix
上万乘上万维的矩阵作逆变换
starts to get kind of slow,
会开始有点慢
and I might then start to
此时我可能开始倾向于
maybe lean in the
direction of gradient descent, but maybe not quite.
梯度下降法 但也不绝对
n equals ten thousand, you can
n等于一万 你可以
sort of convert a ten-thousand-by-ten-thousand matrix.
逆变换一个一万乘一万的矩阵
But if it gets much bigger than that, then, I would probably use gradient descent.
但如果n远大于此 我可能就会使用梯度下降法了
So, if n equals ten
所以如果n等于10^6
to the sixth with a million
有一百万个特征变量
features, then inverting a
那么做百万乘百万的矩阵的逆变换
million-by-million matrix is going
to be very expensive, and
就会变得非常费时间
I would definitely favor gradient descent if you have that many features.
在这种情况下我一定会使用梯度下降法
So exactly how large
所以很难给出一个确定的值
set of features has to be
来决定何时该换成梯度下降法
before you convert a gradient descent, it's hard to give a strict number.
But, for me, it is usually
但是 对我来说通常是
around ten thousand that I might
在一万左右 我会开始考虑换成梯度下降法
start to consider switching over
to gradient descents or maybe,
在一万左右 我会开始考虑换成梯度下降法
some other algorithms that we'll talk about later in this class.
或者我们将在以后讨论到的其他算法
To summarize, so long
总结一下
as the number of features is
只要特征变量的数目并不大
not too large, the normal equation
标准方程是一个很好的
gives us a great alternative method to solve for the parameter theta.
计算参数θ的替代方法
Concretely, so long as
具体地说 只要特征变量数量小于一万
the number of features is less
than 1000, you know, I would
我通常使用标准方程法
use, I would usually is used
in normal equation method rather than, gradient descent.
而不使用梯度下降法
To preview some ideas that
预告一下在之后的课程中我们要讲的
we'll talk about later in this
course, as we get
随着我们要讲的学习算法越来越复杂
to the more complex learning algorithm, for
example, when we talk about
例如 当我们讲到分类算法
classification algorithm, like a logistic regression algorithm,
像逻辑回归算法
We'll see that those algorithm
我们会看到
actually...
实际上对于那些算法
The normal  equation method actually do not work
并不能使用标准方程法
for those more sophisticated
对于那些更复杂的学习算法
learning algorithms, and, we
我们将不得不仍然使用梯度下降法
will have to resort to gradient descent for those algorithms.
So, gradient descent is a very useful algorithm to know.
因此 梯度下降法是一个非常有用的算法
The linear regression will have
可以用在有大量特征变量的线性回归问题
a large number of features and
for some of the other algorithms
或者我们以后在课程中
that we'll see in
会讲到的一些其他的算法
this course, because, for them, the normal
因为 标准方程法不适合或者不能用在它们上
equation method just doesn't apply and doesn't work.
But for this specific model of
但对于这个特定的线性回归模型
linear regression, the normal equation
can give you a alternative
标准方程法是一个
that can be much faster, than gradient descent.
比梯度下降法更快的替代算法
So, depending on the detail of your algortithm,
所以 根据具体的问题
depending of the detail of the problems and
how many features that you have,
以及你的特征变量的数量
both of these algorithms are well worth knowing about.
这两算法都是值得学习的